What do you think when you look at me?
ماذا تعتقد وأنت تنظر إليّ؟
A woman of faith? An expert?
امرأة مؤمنة؟ خبيرة؟
Maybe even a sister.
أو حتى أخت.
Or oppressed,
أو مضطهدة،
brainwashed,
مغسولة الدماغ،
a terrorist.
إرهابية.
Or just an airport security line delay.
أو فقط امرأة متعطلة في طابور التحقق الأمني بالمطار.
That one's actually true.
هذا الأخير حقيقي في الواقع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If some of your perceptions were negative, I don't really blame you.
إذا كانت طريقة إدراككم لي سلبية، فأنا لا ألومكم البتة.
That's just how the media has been portraying
هذا ما داومت وسائل الإعلام في رسم صورته
people who look like me.
لمن هم مثلي.
One study found
وجدت دراسة
that 80 percent of news coverage about Islam and Muslims is negative.
أن 80% من التغطيات الإخبارية عن الإسلام والمسلمين سلبية.
And studies show that Americans say that most don't know a Muslim.
وتوضح دراسات أخرى أن معظم الأمريكيين لا يعرفون مسلمًا بشكل شخصي.
I guess people don't talk to their Uber drivers.
أعتقد أنهم لا يتحدثون لسائقي خدمة أوبر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, for those of you who have never met a Muslim,
حسنًا، لمن لم يقابل منكم مسلمًا من قبل،
it's great to meet you.
إنها فرصة طيبة للقائكم.
Let me tell you who I am.
دعوني أخبركم من أنا.
I'm a mom, a coffee lover --
أنا أم، محبة للقهوة -
double espresso, cream on the side.
أحبها ثقيلة، ومع كريمة على جانبها.
I'm an introvert.
أنا انطوائية.
I'm a wannabe fitness fanatic.
أنا متحمسة مبتدئة لتمارين اللياقة.
And I'm a practicing, spiritual Muslim.
وأنا أمارس إيماني الروحاني كمسلمة.
But not like Lady Gaga says, because baby, I wasn't born this way.
ولكن ليس كما تقول ليدي جاجا، لأنه يا صغيري، أنا لم أجد نفسي هكذا.
It was a choice.
لقد كان اختيارًا.
When I was 17, I decided to come out.
عندما كنت في الـ17، قررت أن أواجه العالم.
No, not as a gay person like some of my friends,
لا، ليس كالمثليين جنسيًا مثل بعض أصدقائي،
but as a Muslim,
لكن كمسلمة.
and decided to start wearing the hijab, my head covering.
وقررت أن أرتدي الحجاب، غطاء رأسي.
My feminist friends were aghast:
صديقاتي كانوا مذعورين:
"Why are you oppressing yourself?"
"لما تغلقين على نفسك؟"
The funny thing was,
الشيء المضحك
it was actually at that time a feminist declaration of independence
أنه في ذلك الوقت كان إعلانا نسويًا بالتحرر
from the pressure I felt as a 17-year-old,
من الضغط الذي شعرت به في الـ17،
to conform to a perfect and unattainable standard of beauty.
للتوافق مع معيار مثالي متعذر من الجمال.
I didn't just passively accept the faith of my parents.
لم أتقبل الإيمان سلبيًا عبر والدي.
I wrestled with the Quran.
لقد كافحت مع القرآن.
I read and reflected and questioned and doubted
قرأت وتدبرت وسألت وشككت
and, ultimately, believed.
وفي النهاية، آمنت.
My relationship with God -- it was not love at first sight.
علاقتي بالله - لم تكن حبًا من أول نظرة.
It was a trust and a slow surrender
لقد كانت ثقة وتسليمًا بطيئًا
that deepened with every reading of the Quran.
تعمقت مع كل قراءة للقرآن.
Its rhythmic beauty sometimes moves me to tears.
جماله الموسيقي يدمعني في كثير من الأحيان.
I see myself in it. I feel that God knows me.
أرى نفسي فيه. أشعر أن الله يعرفني.
Have you ever felt like someone sees you, completely understands you
هل شعرت من قبل أن أحدًا يراك ويفهمك تمامًا
and yet loves you anyway?
ويحبك على أية حال؟
That's how it feels.
كذلك هو شعوري.
And so later, I got married,
ثم تزوجت لاحقًا،
and like all good Egyptians,
و ككل المصريين الجيدين،
started my career as an engineer.
بدأت مساري المهني كمهندسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I later had a child, after getting married,
ثم رُزقت بطفل بعد زواجي،
and I was living essentially the Egyptian-American dream.
وكنت أعيش الحلم المصري الأمريكي.
And then that terrible morning of September, 2001.
حتى جاء هذا الصباح الفظيع في سبتمبر، 2001.
I think a lot of you probably remember exactly where you were that morning.
أعتقد أن كثيرًا منكم ربما يتذكر بالضبط أين كان في ذلك الصباح.
I was sitting in my kitchen finishing breakfast,
أنا كنت في مطبخي أنتهي من الفطور
and I look up on the screen and see the words "Breaking News."
وأشاهد وقد كتب على شاشة التلفاز "خبر عاجل"
There was smoke, airplanes flying into buildings,
كان هناك دخان، طائرات تخترق البنايات،
people jumping out of buildings.
أشخاص يقفزون خارج المباني.
What was this?
ماذا كان ذلك؟
An accident?
حادثة؟
A malfunction?
عطل ما؟
My shock quickly turned to outrage.
صدمتي تحولت سريعًا لثورة غضب.
Who would do this?
من يمكنه القيام بذلك؟
And I switch the channel and I hear,
أغير المحطة وأسمع،
"... Muslim terrorist ...,"
"...إرهابي مسلم...،"
"... in the name of Islam ...,"
"... باسم الإسلام...،"
"... Middle-Eastern descent ...,"
"...من أصول شرق أوسطية...،"
"... jihad ...,"
"....جهاد....،"
"... we should bomb Mecca."
"...يجب أن نغزو مكة."
Oh my God.
يا إلهي.
Not only had my country been attacked,
لم يتعرض وطني لهجوم فحسب،
but in a flash,
ولكن في غمضة عين،
somebody else's actions had turned me from a citizen
أفعال أحدهم حولتني من مواطنة
to a suspect.
لمشتبه بها.
That same day, we had to drive across Middle America
في نفس اليوم، كان علينا أن نقود عبر وسط أمريكا
to move to a new city to start grad school.
لننتقل لمدينة جديدة لبدء الدراسة الجامعية.
And I remember sitting in the passenger seat
وأتذكر جلوسي في مقعد الركاب
as we drove in silence,
ونحن نتحرك في صمت،
crouched as low as I could go in my seat,
منكمشة في مقعدي قدر ما استطعت،
for the first time in my life, afraid for anyone to know I was a Muslim.
لأول مرة في حياتي، خائفة من أن يعرف أي أحد أنني مسلمة.
We moved into our apartment that night in a new town
انتقلنا في تلك الليلة إلى شقتنا في مدينة جديدة
in what felt like a completely different world.
فيما شعرت به كعالم مختلف تمامًا.
And then I was hearing and seeing and reading
ثم كنت أسمع وأرى وأقرأ
warnings from national Muslim organizations
تحذيرات من منظمات وطنية مسلمة
saying things like, "Be alert," "Be aware,"
تقول أشياء مثل، "كن حذرًا،" "ترقب،"
"Stay in well-lit areas," "Don't congregate."
"كن في أماكن مضاءة جيدًا،" "لا تتجمهر."
I stayed inside all week.
ظللت ببيتي طوال الإسبوع.
And then it was Friday that same week,
ثم في يوم الجمعة من نفس الإسبوع،
the day that Muslims congregate for worship.
اليوم الذي يجتمع فيه المسلمون للعبادة.
And again the warnings were, "Don't go that first Friday,
وتأتي التحذيرات مرةً أخرى، "لا تذهبوا إلى صلاة الجمعة هذه المرة،
it could be a target."
فقد تكون الصلاة مستهدفة."
And I was watching the news, wall-to-wall coverage.
وكنت أشاهد الأخبار، جميع التغطيات من أولها لآخرها.
Emotions were so raw, understandably,
كانت العواطف صارخة، لأسباب مفهومة،
and I was also hearing about attacks on Muslims,
وكنت أسمع أيضا عن هجمات على المسلمين،
or people who were perceived to be Muslim, being pulled out
أو عن أشخاص ظُن بهم أنهم مسلمون فتم أخذههم
and beaten in the street.
وضربهم على قارعة الطريق.
Mosques were actually firebombed.
في الواقع، هناك مساجد أٌلقِيَت عليها القنابل.
And I thought, we should just stay home.
واعتقدت أننا يجب أن نظل في البيت فحسب.
And yet, something didn't feel right.
إلا أن هناك شيئًا لم يشعرني بالارتياح.
Because those people who attacked our country
لأن من قاموا بالاعتداء على بلدنا
attacked our country.
قد اعتدوا على بلدنا.
I get it that people were angry at the terrorists.
أتفهم أن الناس كانت غاضبة من الإرهابيين.
Guess what? So was I.
أتدرون؟ وأنا أيضًا.
And so to have to explain yourself all the time isn't easy.
وأن تضطر أن تدافع عن نفسك طوال الوقت، ليس سهلاً.
I don't mind questions. I love questions.
أنا لا أمانع الأسئلة. أنا أحب الأسئلة.
It's the accusations that are tough.
الأمر القاسي هو الاتهامات.
Today we hear people actually saying things like,
في الواقع، نسمع هذه الأيام ناس يقولون أشياء كـ
"There's a problem in this country, and it's called Muslims.
"هناك مشكلة في هذا البلد تسمى المسلمين.
When are we going to get rid of them?"
متى سنتخلص منهم؟"
So, some people want to ban Muslims and close down mosques.
فنهاك من يريد أن يحظر المسلمين ويغلق المساجد.
They talk about my community kind of like we're a tumor
يتحدثون عن مجتمعي المسلم وكأنه ورم
in the body of America.
في جسد أمريكا.
And the only question is, are we malignant or benign?
والسؤال الوحيد هو: هل نحن ورم حميد أم خبيث؟
You know, a malignant tumor you extract altogether,
في حالة الورم الخبيث، تقوم باستئصاله كاملًا،
and a benign tumor you just keep under surveillance.
والورم الحميد تبقيه تحت المراقبة.
The choices don't make sense, because it's the wrong question.
الخيارات لا تُعقل، لأن السؤال خاطيء.
Muslims, like all other Americans, aren't a tumor in the body of America,
المسلمون، مثل كل الأمريكيين الآخرين، ليسوا ورمًا في الجسد الأمريكي،
we're a vital organ.
نحن عضوٌ فاعل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
أشكركم.
Muslims are inventors and teachers,
المسلمون مخترعون ومعلمون،
first responders and Olympic athletes.
تجدهم في فرق الإنقاذ ورياضيون أوليمبيون.
Now, is closing down mosques going to make America safer?
الآن، هل غلق المساجد سيجعل أمريكا أكثر أمانًا؟
It might free up some parking spots,
ربما غلقها سيوفر بعض الأماكن لركن السيارات،
but it will not end terrorism.
ولكن ذلك لن ينهي الإرهاب.
Going to a mosque regularly is actually linked
في الواقع، الذهاب إلى المسجد بانتظام مرتبط
to having more tolerant views of people of other faiths
بتبني وجهات نظر أكثر تسامحًا تجاه أصحاب المذاهب الإيمانية الأخرى
and greater civic engagement.
وباندماج مدني أكثر.
And as one police chief in the Washington, DC area
كما أخبرني مؤخرًا قائد للشرطة
recently told me,
في العاصمة واشنطن،
people don't actually get radicalized at mosques.
أن الناس في الواقع لا تتعصب في المساجد.
They get radicalized in their basement or bedroom, in front of a computer.
إنهم يتعصبون في الأقبية أو في غرف نومهم وهم أمام الحاسوب.
And what you find about the radicalization process
وما تكتشفه حول عملية التعصب
is it starts online,
أنها تبدأ على الإنترنت،
but the first thing that happens
ولكن ما يحدث في البداية
is the person gets cut off from their community,
أن الشخص ينعزل عن مجتمعه،
from even their family,
وحتى عن عائلته،
so that the extremist group can brainwash them
حتى يتسنى للجماعات المتطرفة أن تغسل دماغه
into believing that they, the terrorists, are the true Muslims,
حتى يعتقد أن الإرهابيين هم المسلمون حقًا،
and everyone else who abhors their behavior and ideology
وكل من يمقت سلوكهم وفكرهم
are sellouts or apostates.
هم خونة ومرتدين.
So if we want to prevent radicalization,
فلو أننا نريد أن نمنع التعصب،
we have to keep people going to the mosque.
يجب أن نحافظ على ذهاب الناس إلى المسجد.
Now, some will still argue Islam is a violent religion.
الآن، سيستمر البعض بمجادلة أن الإسلام دين عنف.
After all, a group like ISIS bases its brutality on the Quran.
فكما يظهر، جماعة كـداعش ترتكن في وحشيتها على القرآن كمرجعيتهم.
Now, as a Muslim, as a mother, as a human being,
الآن، كمسلمة وكأم وكإنسانة،
I think we need to do everything we can to stop a group like ISIS.
أعتقد أننا يجب أن نبذل ما في وسعنا لإيقاف مجموعة كداعش.
But we would be giving in to their narrative
ولكننا سنكون قد خضعنا لرؤيتهم
if we cast them as representatives of a faith of 1.6 billion people.
إذا اعتبرناهم ممثلون عن دين يؤمن به 1.6 مليار من البشر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
أشكركم.
ISIS has as much to do with Islam
علاقة داعش بالإسلام
as the Ku Klux Klan has to do with Christianity.
بنفس قدر علاقة كو كلوكس كلان بالمسيحية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Both groups claim to base their ideology on their holy book.
كلتا المجموعتان يدعيان أنهما يستمدان فكرهما من كتابهما المقدس.
But when you look at them, they're not motivated
ولكن عندما تنظر إليهما، لا تجد ما يحفزهما
by what they read in their holy book.
فيما يقرأونه في كتابهما المقدس.
It's their brutality that makes them read these things into the scripture.
إنها وحشيتهم التي تجعلهم يلوون ما في النص ليوافقهم.
Recently, a prominent imam told me a story that really took me aback.
مؤخرا، أخبرني إمام بارز بقصة أثرت بي كثيراً.
He said that a girl came to him
أخبرني أن فتاة جاءت إليه
because she was thinking of going to join ISIS.
لأنها كانت تفكر في الالتحاق بداعش.
And I was really surprised and asked him,
وكنت مندهشة حقًا وسألته،
had she been in contact with a radical religious leader?
هل كانت على اتصال بقائد جماعة متعصبة؟
And he said the problem was quite the opposite,
فأجابني أن الأمر كان على العكس تمامًا،
that every cleric that she had talked to had shut her down
فقد خذلها كل رجل دين تحدثت معه
and said that her rage, her sense of injustice in the world,
وقال أن غضبها، وإحساسها بالظلم في العالم
was just going to get her in trouble.
كان سيلقي بها في المشاكل.
And so with nowhere to channel and make sense of this anger,
وهكذا بدون سبيل يستنزف هذا الغضب،
she was a prime target to be exploited
كانت هدفًا ممتازًا ليُستغل
by extremists promising her a solution.
من قبل متطرفون يعدونها بحل.
What this imam did was to connect her back to God and to her community.
ما قام به هذا الإمام هو إعادة صلتها بالله وبمجتمعها.
He didn't shame her for her rage -- instead, he gave her constructive ways
لم يلومها على غضبها -- بدلاً من ذلك، قام بإعطائها طرقًا بناءة
to make real change in the world.
لتقوم بتغيير حقيقي في العالم.
What she learned at that mosque prevented her from going to join ISIS.
ما تعلمته في المسجد منعها من الانضمام لداعش.
I've told you a little bit
قد أخبرتكم قليلاً
about how Islamophobia affects me and my family.
عن كيف تأثرت حياتي وأسرتي بالإسلاموفوبيا (الخوف من الإسلام)
But how does it impact ordinary Americans?
ولكن كيف يؤثر ذلك على الأمريكي العادي؟
How does it impact everyone else?
وكيف يؤثر ذلك على كل شخص آخر؟
How does consuming fear 24 hours a day affect the health of our democracy,
كيف يؤثر تعاطي الخوف طوال ساعات اليوم على صحة نظامنا الديمقراطي؟
the health of our free thought?
على صحة فكرنا الحر؟
Well, one study -- actually, several studies in neuroscience --
حسنًا، في دراسة -- في الواقع عدة دراسات في علم الأعصاب --
show that when we're afraid, at least three things happen.
توضح أن هناك على الأقل ثلاثة أشياء تحدث عندما نخاف.
We become more accepting of authoritarianism,
نكون أكثر تقبلاً للاستبداد،
conformity and prejudice.
للامتثال والتحيز.
One study showed that when subjects were exposed to news stories
أوضحت دراسة أن بتعرض العينة لقصص الأخبار السلبية
that were negative about Muslims,
عن المسلمين،
they became more accepting of military attacks on Muslim countries
أصبحوا أكثر تقبلاً للهجمات العسكرية على البلدان المسلمة
and policies that curtail the rights of American Muslims.
وأيضًا للسياسات التي تنتقص من حقوق المسلمين الأمريكيين.
Now, this isn't just academic.
الآن، هذه ليست مجرد دراسة أكاديمية.
When you look at when anti-Muslim sentiment spiked
فعندما تنظر متى برزت العواطف العدائية تجاه المسلمين
between 2001 and 2013,
بين العام 2001 و 2013،
it happened three times,
ستجد أن هذا حدث ثلاث مرات،
but it wasn't around terrorist attacks.
ولكنها لم تكن بسبب هجمات إرهابية.
It was in the run up to the Iraq War and during two election cycles.
كانت أثناء تصعيد الحرب على العراق وبين دورتين انتخابيتين.
So Islamophobia isn't just the natural response to Muslim terrorism
إذًا فالإسلاموفوبيا ليست استجابة طبيعية للإرهاب الإسلامي
as I would have expected.
كما كنت أتوقع.
It can actually be a tool of public manipulation,
فيمكنها أن تكون أداة للتلاعب بالجماهير،
eroding the very foundation of a free society,
وجارفة لأساس المجتمع الحر،
which is rational and well-informed citizens.
والتي تتمثل في المواطن العقلاني المطلع.
Muslims are like canaries in the coal mine.
المسلمون كطائر الكناري في منجم الفحم.
We might be the first to feel it,
ربما نكون نحن أول من نشعر به،
but the toxic air of fear is harming us all.
ولكن هواء الخوف المسموم يؤذينا جميعا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And assigning collective guilt
وتحميل الذنب الجماعي
isn't just about having to explain yourself all the time.
ليس فقط أن تدافع عن نفسك طوال الوقت.
Deah and his wife Yusor were a young married couple
ضياء وزوجته يسر، كانا زوجين في مقتبل العمر
living in Chapel Hill, North Carolina,
يعيشان في تشابل هيل في كارولاينا الشمالية،
where they both went to school.
حيث كانا يذهبان معًا إلى الجامعة.
Deah was an athlete.
ضياء كان رياضيًا.
He was in dental school, talented, promising ...
كان يدرس طب الأسنان، موهوب، وواعد ...
And his sister would tell me that he was the sweetest,
وأخته تخبرني أنه كان ألطف
most generous human being she knew.
وأكثر من عرفتهم من البشر كرمًا.
She was visiting him there and he showed her his resume,
كانت تزوره هناك وأراها سيرته الذاتية،
and she was amazed.
وأصابها الذهول.
She said, "When did my baby brother become such an accomplished young man?"
قالت، "متى أصبح أخي الصغير بكل هذه الإنجازات؟"
Just a few weeks after Suzanne's visit to her brother and his new wife,
بعد زيارة سوزان لأخيها وزوجته الجديدة بعدة أسابيع،
their neighbor,
جارهما،
Craig Stephen Hicks,
كريج ستيفن هيكس،
murdered them,
قام بقتلهما،
as well as Yusor's sister, Razan, who was visiting for the afternoon,
وقتل معهما رزان أخت يسر والتي كانت تزورهما في الظهيرة،
in their apartment,
في شقتهما،
execution style,
على طراز الإعدام،
after posting anti-Muslim statements on his Facebook page.
وذلك بعد نشر عبارات معادية للمسلمين على صفحته على الفيسبوك.
He shot Deah eight times.
أطلق النار على ضياء ثمان مرات.
So bigotry isn't just immoral, it can even be lethal.
إذًا فالتعصب ليس فقط أمرًا لا أخلاقيًا ولكنه قد يكون مميتًا.
So, back to my story.
فعودة لقصتي.
What happened after 9/11?
ما الذي حدث بعد 9/11؟
Did we go to the mosque or did we play it safe and stay home?
هل ذهبنا إلى المسجد أم آثرنا السلامة ومكثنا في بيوتنا؟
Well, we talked it over,
حسنًا، قمنا بمناقشة الأمر،
and it might seem like a small decision, but to us,
ربما كان قرارًا بسيطًا، ولكن بالنسبة لنا،
it was about what kind of America we wanted to leave for our kids:
كان يعبرعن نوعية أمريكا التي نريد أن نتركها لأبنائنا:
one that would control us by fear
أمريكا التي قد تحكمنا بالخوف
or one where we were practicing our religion freely.
أو أمريكا التي كنا نمارس فيها ديننا بحرية.
So we decided to go to the mosque.
فقررنا أن نذهب إلى المسجد.
And we put my son in his car seat,
ووضعنا ابننا في مقعده بالسيارة،
buckled him in, and we drove silently, intensely, to the mosque.
ربطنا حزام أمانه وقدنا بصمت و بتوتر إلى المسجد.
I took him out, I took off my shoes, I walked into the prayer hall
أخرجته خارج السيارة، خلعت حذائي ومشيت إلى مكان الصلاة في المسجد
and what I saw made me stop.
وما رأيته جعلني أتوقف.
The place was completely full.
المكان كان ممتلئًا عن آخره.
And then the imam made an announcement,
ثم قام الإمام بالحديث،
thanking and welcoming our guests,
شاكرًا ومرحبًا بضيوفنا،
because half the congregation
لأن نصف التجمع
were Christians, Jews, Buddhists, atheists,
كانوا مسيحيين ويهود وبوذيين وملحدين،
people of faith and no faith,
من يؤمنون بالله ومن يكفرون به،
who had come not to attack us, but to stand in solidarity with us.
الذين أتوا لا ليهاجمونا ولكن ليتضامنوا معنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I just break down at this time.
انهرت عند تلك اللحظة.
These people were there because they chose courage and compassion
هؤلاء كانوا هناك لأنهم اختاروا الشجاعة والتعاطف
over panic and prejudice.
على الذعر والتعصب.
What will you choose?
ماذا ستختارون؟
What will you choose at this time of fear and bigotry?
ماذا ستختارون في هذا الوقت من الخوف والتعصب؟
Will you play it safe?
هل ستؤثرون السلامة؟
Or will you join those who say
أم ستنضمون لمن يقولون
we are better than that?
نحن أفضل من ذلك؟
Thank you.
أشكركم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you so much.
أشكركم شكرًا جزيلاً
Helen Walters: So Dalia, you seem to have struck a chord.
هيلين ولترز: داليا، يبدو أنك لمست الوتر.
But I wonder,
ولكني أتساءل،
what would you say to those who might argue
ماذا تقولين لمن يجادلون
that you're giving a TED Talk,
أنه بما أنك ألقيت بحديث بمؤتمر TED،
you're clearly a deep thinker,
فإنك من الواضح مفكرة قديرة،
you work at a fancy think tank,
وتعملين بملتقى خبرة خيالي،
you're an exception, you're not the rule.
وإنك استثنائية، لذلك فأنت لا تمثلين القاعدة.
What would you say to those people?
ماذا تقولين لهؤلاء الناس؟
Dalia Mogahed: I would say, don't let this stage distract you,
داليا مجاهد: سأقول، لا تدعوا وقوفي على المنصة يخدعكم،
I'm completely ordinary.
أنا امرأة عادية تمامًا.
I'm not an exception.
أنا لست استثنائية،
My story is not unusual.
وقصتي ليست بالغريبة.
I am as ordinary as they come.
أنا عادية مثل أي أحد.
When you look at Muslims around the world --
عندما تنظرين إلى المسلمين حول العالم --
and I've done this, I've done the largest study ever done
وأنا قمت بدراسة هي أكبر دراسة تمت
on Muslims around the world --
عن المسلمين حول العالم --
people want ordinary things.
الناس ترغب بأمور عادية.
They want prosperity for their family,
يريدون العيش الكريم لأسرهم،
they want jobs
يريدون وظائف
and they want to live in peace.
ويريدون العيش بسلام.
So I am not in any way an exception.
لذلك فأنا لست استثناء بأي حال.
When you meet people who seem like an exception to the rule,
عندما تقابلين من يبدون كاستثناء للقاعدة،
oftentimes it's that the rule is broken,
فغالبًا تكون تلك القاعدة قد كُسرت،
not that they're an exception to it.
ليس الأمر أنهم استثناء عليها.
HW: Thank you so much. Dalia Mogahed.
هـيلين ولترز: أشكرك شكرًا جزيلاً داليـا مـجاهـد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)